<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss version='2.0' xmlns:atom='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom'>
<channel>
<atom:link href='http://locusofctrl.github.io/' rel='self' type='application/rss+xml'/>
<title>
After Sol
</title>
<link>
http://locusofctrl.github.io/
</link>
<description>
notes and musings
</description>
<lastBuildDate>
Wed, 16 Jan 2019 00:30:58 -0800
</lastBuildDate>
<generator>
clj-rss
</generator>
<item>
<guid>
http://locusofctrl.github.io/blog/posts-output/2019-01-15-seger-paper/
</guid>
<link>
http://locusofctrl.github.io/blog/posts-output/2019-01-15-seger-paper/
</link>
<title>
A Classic Genetic Model of Sexual Selection
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/blog/img/seger1985/pheasant.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;pheasant courting&quot; idth=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;426&quot; /&gt; &lt;figcaption&gt;Male Lady Amherst's pheasant courting a female (photo: Henry Koh)&lt;/figcaption&gt; &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;An anthropologist &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/LTF&amp;#95;01'&gt;friend of mine&lt;/a&gt; runs a online book club, where we were going through Robert Trivers' book &lt;a href='https://www.amazon.com/Natural-Selection-Social-Theory-Evolution/dp/0195130626'&gt;Natural Selection and Social Theory&lt;/a&gt; (also available for free &lt;a href='http://roberttrivers.com/Robert&amp;#95;Trivers/Publications&amp;#95;files/libro&amp;#95;trivers.pdf'&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), which is a collection of some of his papers with interesting and often humorous details thrown in as a preface to each chapter. Trivers was one of the greats who came out of the 1970s sociobiology wave, and I obviously recommend the book as well as any other one by him.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The book includes a paper Trivers co-authored with Jon Seger that makes a mathematical argument that females ought to chose genes benefiting their daughters first, even if it entails some expense to their male offspring. Trivers had a knack for framing his theories in terms of &lt;i&gt;conflict&lt;/i&gt; (he  coined the term &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parent%E2%80%93offspring&amp;#95;conflict'&gt;&quot;parent-offspring conflict&quot;&lt;/a&gt;), and this was a case of a conflict between male and female genes. While trying to understand the mathematical argument (developed mostly by Seger), I have descended into the rabbit hole that is &lt;i&gt;two-locus model&lt;/i&gt; of sexual selection. The topic had long fascinated me, so I thought it would be a good exercise to understand the paper and then write about it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the &quot;good genes for daughters&quot; paper, Seger relies on his previous work where he extends Mark Kirkpatrick's model to allow slightly more realistic &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lek&amp;#95;mating'&gt;lek-like&lt;/a&gt; mating. In fact, it is &lt;a href='https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1558-5646.1985.tb05685.x'&gt;that previous paper&lt;/a&gt; by Seger that will be the subject of today's post, though the reasoning is equally applicable to &lt;a href='https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1558-5646.1982.tb05003.x'&gt;the better-cited one&lt;/a&gt; by Kirkpatrick. I like Seger's presentation of Kirkpatrick's model because it is more straightforward, and because, in my opinion, he hits on something important with his focus on lek-like mating. I will also make use of Chapter 2 of &lt;a href='https://www.amazon.com/Evolutionary-Theory-Mathematical-Conceptual-Foundations/dp/0878937021'&gt;Sean H. Rice's book&lt;/a&gt;  on evolutionary modeling. You can download the Mathematica notebooks I made while writing this post from &lt;a href='https://github.com/LocusOfCtrl/notebooks'&gt;this repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;seger's&amp;#95;paper&quot;&gt;Seger's Paper&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;h4 id=&quot;historical&amp;#95;notes&quot;&gt;Historical Notes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seger builds on &lt;a href='https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1558-5646.1982.tb05003.x'&gt;Kirkpatrick's model&lt;/a&gt; which, along with &lt;a href='https://www.pnas.org/content/78/6/3721'&gt;Lande's&lt;/a&gt;, was hailed as a breakthrough in a long-running argument, started in 1930 by R.A. Fisher, on whether sexual selection can become a &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fisherian&amp;#95;runaway'&gt;runaway process&lt;/a&gt; that would drive evolution of arbitrary ornaments on males without regard to individual fitness (which, in extreme cases, would be to the decrement of the population). Fisher &lt;a href='https://archive.org/details/geneticaltheoryo031631mbp/page/n159'&gt;conjectured that it can&lt;/a&gt; but did not provide a formal proof. Fifty years later, the proponents of &quot;good genes&quot; hypotheses (of which Hamilton-Zuk &lt;a href='http://science.sciencemag.org/content/218/4570/384.long'&gt;parasite hypothesis&lt;/a&gt; and Zahavi's &lt;a href='https://www.amazon.com/Handicap-Principle-Missing-Darwins-Puzzle/dp/0195129148'&gt;handicap principle&lt;/a&gt; are probably the most famous) argued that adaptationist natural selection should prevail. Lande's and Kirkpatrick's models proved Fisher correct, showing that the &quot;decadent&quot; runaway process can indeed occur, but this did not disprove any of the competing hypotheses, which may also describe real evolutionary forces.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Further developments of Kirkpatrick's model yielded mixed results: for example, assigning even small cost to female choice breaks down the runaway process, while setting a realistic mutation rate results in a single point of equilibrium rather than in a continuous line. On the other hand, &lt;a href='https://doi.org/10.1006/tpbi.1994.1001'&gt;mate choice copying&lt;/a&gt; (which can be said to be  a form of culture) was shown to reinforce the Fisherian process. In summary, although we know today that Fisherian runaways are theoretically possible, questions remain how much of the diversity in secondary sexual characteristics between various species is actually due to this particular process. In the light of this, Seger's analysis of lek mating is particularly interesting because, intuitively speaking, leks ought to reduce the cost of choosing a mate for females.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4 id=&quot;basic&amp;#95;model&quot;&gt;Basic Model&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assume we're dealing with a haploid organism (for any non-biologist reading this: haploids carry one strand of DNA while diploids carry two, one from each parent). There are two genes, &lt;code&gt;$T$&lt;/code&gt; (&quot;trait&quot;) that is only expressed in males and &lt;code&gt;$P$&lt;/code&gt; (&quot;preference&quot;) that is only expressed in females (though both sexes carry them). The &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; allele (gene variant) gives males a fancy ornament which appeals to &lt;code&gt;$P&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; females but not to &lt;code&gt;$P&amp;#95;1$&lt;/code&gt; females who disregard it. Importantly, the &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; allele also decreases male survival by a fraction &lt;code&gt;$s$&lt;/code&gt;. All females have equal survival rate, regardless of genotype.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I will label the allele frequencies in the population with the respective lowercase letters. It's clear that &lt;code&gt;$t&amp;#95;1 = 1 - t&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;$p&amp;#95;1 = 1 - p&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt;. Let &lt;code&gt;$\def\sp{&amp;#94;}t&amp;#95;2\sp{m}$&lt;/code&gt; be the fraction of &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; males after selection (i.e. ones that survive to maturity). Then,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;$$\begin{eqnarray} t&amp;#95;1\sp{m} &amp;=&amp; t&amp;#95;1 ⁄ M \tag{1a} &amp;#92;&amp;#92; t&amp;#95;2\sp{m} &amp;=&amp; (1 - s) t&amp;#95;2 ⁄ M, \tag{1b} \end{eqnarray}$$&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;where &lt;code&gt;$M = t&amp;#95;1 + &amp;#40;1 - s&amp;#41; t&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; is the average male viability.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let's consider how many of the offspring will carry the &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; allele. From &lt;a href='https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hardy%E2%80%93Weinberg&amp;#95;principle'&gt;Hardy-Weinberg principle&lt;/a&gt;, it should be clear that we need to take the number of genetically homogeneous mating pairs and add to it one half the number of heterogeneous pairs (the latter have 50% chance of producing offspring carrying &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; in this haploid model). Note that this is the same as adding up all pairings with &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; allele counted separately for each sex and dividing by two (the homogeneous pairs will be counted twice). Thus, the expected frequencies of &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;1$&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; in the next generation are:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;$$\begin{eqnarray} t&amp;#95;1' &amp;=&amp; (t&amp;#95;1\sp{m} p&amp;#95;1 + U&amp;#95;{21} p&amp;#95;2 + t&amp;#95;1) ⁄ 2 \tag{2a} &amp;#92;&amp;#92; t&amp;#95;2' &amp;=&amp; (t&amp;#95;2\sp{m} p&amp;#95;1 + U&amp;#95;{22} p&amp;#95;2 + t&amp;#95;2) ⁄ 2, \tag{2b} \end{eqnarray}$$&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;where &lt;code&gt;$U&amp;#95;{21}$&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;$U&amp;#95;{22}$&lt;/code&gt; are the fractions of &lt;code&gt;$P&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; females that mate with &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;1$&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; males, respectively. Since &lt;code&gt;$P&amp;#95;1$&lt;/code&gt; females mate randomly, their pairings with males carrying the allele of interest depend on the frequency of those males. Also note that because female survival does not depend on allele, the frequency of pairings with &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; females is simply &lt;code&gt;$t&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt;. One can also derive these equations more formally using the &lt;i&gt;mating table&lt;/i&gt; which I describe in &lt;a href='#numerical&amp;#95;results'&gt;a section below&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now Seger does not actually calculate the overall frequencies of &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;1$&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; in the next generation&amp;mdash;instead, he calculates the reproductive successes of males, labeling them &lt;code&gt;$V&amp;#95;1$&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;$V&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt;. This results in exactly the same equilibrium lines, but produces wrong fitness estimates outside the equilibrium. I thought it would be interesting to look at relative fitness of &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; outside the equilibrium both because the equilibrium may not always be stable and because the precise coordinates of the equilibrium are unlikely to hold in the real world where there are many different evolutionary forces acting simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4 id=&quot;female&amp;#95;choice&quot;&gt;Female Choice&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;I haven't given a precise definition of&lt;code&gt;$U&amp;#95;{21}$&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;$U&amp;#95;{22}$&lt;/code&gt; yet because it depends on the model we're about to study. Kirkpatrick's model assumes that &lt;code&gt;$P&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; females mate at random like the &lt;code&gt;$P&amp;#95;1$&lt;/code&gt; females except the former tend to prefer &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; males by a factor &lt;code&gt;$a&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; relative to &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;1$&lt;/code&gt;. This gives the following equations:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;$$\begin{eqnarray} U&amp;#95;{21} &amp;=&amp; t&amp;#95;1\sp{m} ⁄ (t&amp;#95;1\sp{m} + a&amp;#95;2 t&amp;#95;2\sp{m}) \tag{3a} &amp;#92;&amp;#92; U&amp;#95;{22} &amp;=&amp; a&amp;#95;2 t&amp;#95;2\sp{m} ⁄ (t&amp;#95;1\sp{m} + a&amp;#95;2 t&amp;#95;2\sp{m}). \tag{3b} \end{eqnarray}$$&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Seger notes that this implies no dependence of female preference on the relative frequencies of the two kinds of males, something that is somewhat unlikely in the real world, unless the &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; trait gives &quot;an enhancement of the 'apparency'&quot; to the males carrying it, for example long-distance vocalization that works on &lt;code&gt;$P&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; females but not on &lt;code&gt;$P&amp;#95;1$&lt;/code&gt;. In reality, a choosy female would probably continue sampling males for a longer time than a non-choosy one, especially if &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; males are rare.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To account for this problem, Seger introduces a &quot;best-of-N&quot; model where males are clustered in groups (leks) of size &lt;code&gt;$N$&lt;/code&gt; and females mate with one of the males in such a group. He reasons as follows: Suppose two types of males, &lt;code&gt;$p$&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;$q,$&lt;/code&gt; are found in leks of two. Then there will be three types of leks with frequencies {&lt;code&gt;$p\sp{2}, 2 p q, q\sp{2}$&lt;/code&gt;}. A female that mates randomly will choose &lt;code&gt;$p$&lt;/code&gt; males at a frequency &lt;code&gt;$p\sp{2} + pq$&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;$= p&amp;#40;p + q&amp;#41; = p.$&lt;/code&gt; A female that always prefers &lt;code&gt;$p$&lt;/code&gt; males when given a choice will choose &lt;code&gt;$p$&lt;/code&gt; males at a frequency &lt;code&gt;$1 - q\sp{2}$&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;$= 1 - &amp;#40;1-p&amp;#41;q$&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;$= 1 - q + pq$&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code&gt;$= p + pq.$&lt;/code&gt; Seger then adds a factor &lt;code&gt;$c$&lt;/code&gt; before the &lt;code&gt;$pq$&lt;/code&gt; term which given &lt;code&gt;$c=0$&lt;/code&gt; implies fully random mating, and given &lt;code&gt;$c=1$&lt;/code&gt; implies consistent preference towards &lt;code&gt;$p$&lt;/code&gt; males. Re-labeling &lt;code&gt;$p$&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;$t&amp;#95;2\sp{m}$&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;$q$&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;$t&amp;#95;1\sp{m}$&lt;/code&gt;, we get the following:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;$$\begin{eqnarray} U&amp;#95;{21} &amp;=&amp; t&amp;#95;1\sp{m} - c t&amp;#95;1\sp{m} t&amp;#95;2\sp{m} \tag{4a} &amp;#92;&amp;#92; U&amp;#95;{22} &amp;=&amp; t&amp;#95;2\sp{m} + c t&amp;#95;1\sp{m} t&amp;#95;2\sp{m}. \tag{4b} \end{eqnarray}$$&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For leks of size greater than two, we simplify things by assuming &lt;code&gt;$c=1$&lt;/code&gt;. Then,&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;$$\begin{eqnarray} U&amp;#95;{21} &amp;=&amp; t&amp;#95;1\sp{m N} \tag{5a} &amp;#92;&amp;#92; U&amp;#95;{22} &amp;=&amp; 1 - t&amp;#95;1\sp{m N}. \tag{5b} \end{eqnarray}$$&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4 id=&quot;fitness&amp;#95;equilibria&quot;&gt;Fitness Equilibria&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are now ready to calculate the fitness and see if our results compare with Seger's. The fitness equations for the two trait alleles are simply their frequency in generation &lt;code&gt;$n+1$&lt;/code&gt; divided by their frequency in generation &lt;code&gt;$n$&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;$$\begin{eqnarray} W&amp;#95;{1} &amp;=&amp; t'&amp;#95;1 ⁄ t&amp;#95;1 \tag{6a} &amp;#92;&amp;#92; W&amp;#95;{2} &amp;=&amp; t'&amp;#95;2 ⁄ t&amp;#95;2. \tag{6b} \end{eqnarray}$$&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Plugging equations 1, 2, and 3 (for Kirkpatrick's random mating model) or 1, 2, and 4 (for Seger's best-of-two model), setting &lt;code&gt;$W&amp;#95;1 = W&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; and solving for &lt;code&gt;$p&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; gives the equilibrium equation (contour of equal fitness). I plotted it in Mathematica for different values of &lt;code&gt;$a&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;$c$&lt;/code&gt; respectively and got the following:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/img/seger1985/seger-fig12a.svg?sanitize=true&quot; width=&quot;590&quot; height=&quot;270&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The left pane shows Kirkpatrick's model and the right pane shows Seger's model. This exactly corresponds to figures 1a and 2a in the paper. Seger makes an additional plot where he sets &lt;code&gt;$p&amp;#95;2 = 0.5$&lt;/code&gt; and shows fitness &lt;code&gt;$W$&lt;/code&gt; as a function of &lt;code&gt;$t&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt;, the frequency of ornamented males:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/img/seger1985/seger-fig12b.svg?sanitize=true&quot; width=&quot;590&quot; height=&quot;170&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The conclusion Seger draws here is that Kirkpatrick's model (left pane) results in a stable equilibrium. It's easy to see why: if &lt;code&gt;$W&amp;#95;2 &amp;gt; W&amp;#95;1$&lt;/code&gt;, then &lt;code&gt;$t&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; will increase until the population ends up in the point where the two curves cross. On the other hand, if &lt;code&gt;$W&amp;#95;1 &amp;gt; W&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt;, then &lt;code&gt;$t&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; will decrease until, again, the equilibrium point is reached. Precisely the opposite applies to the right-side pane (best-of-two model), hence it corresponds to an unstable (divergent) equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h4 id=&quot;fitness&amp;#95;landscapes&quot;&gt;Fitness Landscapes&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wasn't completely satisfied with the boring-looking equilibrium lines  and decided to make a plot that Seger didn't make. Specifically, I wanted a contoured density plot that would show relative fitness of &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; allele with respect to &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;1$&lt;/code&gt;. Unfortunately, Mathematica does not provide an easy way to make a nice exportable graphic out of this type of plot, so I had to steal code from &lt;a href='https://pages.uoregon.edu/noeckel/computernotes/Mathematica/contourDensityPlot.html'&gt;Jens Nöckel's page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/img/seger1985/seger-contours.svg?sanitize=true&quot; width=&quot;590&quot; height=&quot;270&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The left pane shows Kirkpatrick's model with &lt;code&gt;$a&amp;#95;2 = 3$&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;code&gt;$P&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; females mate randomly but have a &lt;code&gt;$3\times$&lt;/code&gt; preference bias towards &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; males) and the right pane shows Seger's best-of-two model with &lt;code&gt;$c = 1$&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;code&gt;$P&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; females always prefer the &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; male when given a choice). In both cases, &lt;code&gt;$s = 0.4$&lt;/code&gt; (the survival rate of &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; males is 60% that of &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;1$&lt;/code&gt; males). The arrows show the approximate trajectories of evolution (longer arrows mean faster evolution). The arrows are not perfectly horizontal because there is gamete-level correlation between the frequency of males expressing the trait and the frequency of females that prefer it. I explain this in detail in a following section. The dashed lines are simply contours with equal level of relative fitness. The color of the plot is mapped to &lt;i&gt;log relative-fitness&lt;/i&gt; (calculated as &lt;code&gt;$log&amp;#91;W&amp;#95;2⁄W&amp;#95;1&amp;#93;$&lt;/code&gt;), with red meaning that &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; allele is winning while blue meaning that &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;1$&lt;/code&gt; allele is winning. The thick black line is the fitness equilibrium.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, I wanted to make a plot for leks of sizes greater than two. While very large leks are rare in nature, most have more than two males in them!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/img/seger1985/seger-contours-N.svg?sanitize=true&quot; width=&quot;590&quot; height=&quot;270&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The left pane corresponds to leks of size &lt;code&gt;$N = 3$&lt;/code&gt;, and the right one to &lt;code&gt;$N = 6$&lt;/code&gt;. The equilibrium had shifted significantly, and it's no longer a straight line. The important thing to note here is just how strong Lande-Fisher runaway effect can be in large leks assuming the frequency of trait-preferring females exceeds the equilibrium threshold.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;numerical&amp;#95;results&quot;&gt;Numerical Results&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The nature of runaway process appears to imply that the frequency of females exhibiting stronger trait preference should increase together with the frequency of males carrying the trait. To evaluate exactly the degree of correlation between the two is not easy, however, because of the complexity of the calculation. Fortunately, it can be estimated by numerically solving three difference equations: trait, preference, and covariance between the two. Seger's paper does not show results of the numerical calculations (except in the context of stability analysis), but Kirkpatrick's one does.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We begin by building a table that lets us precisely predict the frequency of various allele combinations among the offspring:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/img/seger1985/mating-table.svg?sanitize=true&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here, &lt;code&gt;$x&amp;#95;{11}$&lt;/code&gt; is simply a shorthand for frequency of the &lt;code&gt;$T&amp;#95;1 P&amp;#95;1$&lt;/code&gt; genotype. The &lt;code&gt;$r$&lt;/code&gt; variable is the degree of recombination between the trait and preference loci (zero means the loci never recombine, while one means they always recombine). I will assume that &lt;code&gt;$r = 0.5$&lt;/code&gt;, that is the trait and the preference genes are on different chromosomes. The remaining variables should be familiar. Seger and Kirkpatrick give a slightly different-looking table, but I prefer the format used in &lt;a href='https://www.amazon.com/Evolutionary-Theory-Mathematical-Conceptual-Foundations/dp/0878937021'&gt;Sean H. Rice's book&lt;/a&gt; as it is more clear, in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;By multiplying the frequency column and the genotype columns that include the allele of interest and then summing the result, we can obtain recurrence expressions for &lt;code&gt;$t'&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;$p'&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;$D'$&lt;/code&gt;, where &lt;code&gt;$D = x&amp;#95;{11} - t&amp;#95;1 p&amp;#95;1$&lt;/code&gt;, i.e. the deviation between the naively expected genotype frequency and the actual one (&lt;code&gt;$D$&lt;/code&gt; is also called &lt;i&gt;linkage disequilibrium&lt;/i&gt;). The expression for &lt;code&gt;$t'&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; is the same as in Equation 2b. The expressions for &lt;code&gt;$p'&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; and especially &lt;code&gt;$D'$&lt;/code&gt; are more complicated. Luckily, Mathematica can handle this complexity. We can then plug the three expressions into &lt;code&gt;RecurrenceTable&lt;/code&gt;, set the initial values for the three variables, and solve the system numerically. Repeating this process for different initial values of &lt;code&gt;$p'&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;$t'&amp;#95;2$&lt;/code&gt; gives us the figure below:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/img/seger1985/seger-recurrence.png&quot; width=&quot;590&quot; height=&quot;289&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The left pane is the (familiar by now) Kirkpatrick model, while the right pane is Seger's model with &lt;code&gt;$N = 3$&lt;/code&gt;. Each dot corresponds to one generation, so the larger the distance between the dots, the faster the evolution. The orange traces all begin on the left-hand side and &quot;evolve&quot; to the right, while the blue traces begin on the right-hand side and &quot;evolve&quot; to the left. Note the slowdown of evolution near the stable equilibrium in the left pane. Also note that while correlation between trait and preference exists, it is not very strong (the slope of the traces is fairly small).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;last&amp;#95;words&quot;&gt;Last Words&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;The main lesson I draw from this analysis is the somewhat obvious one: Lande-Fisher runaway process is a stronger force with lek-style mating, and it is particularly strong in large leks. For a vivid example of mating with lek size of two, see &lt;a href='https://www.facebook.com/Birds.Lovers.1/videos/1003571246388699/'&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt; showing such mating in the greater bird-of-paradise.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This concludes my exploration of Seger's paper. In the next episode, I will talk either about the Seger-Trivers &quot;good genes for daughters&quot; paper or about evolution of leks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Tue, 15 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0800
</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
